this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Robert bloomin editor
of software engineering radio if you're
hearing this that means you're a
listener of the show but have you ever
thought about being a host it's a great
way to talk to some of the most
interesting people in the industry and
get 30 to 40 thousand people to hear
your thoughts
contact us team @ SC - radio net for
more information are you looking for a
better way to track your engineering
backlog do you want a project management
tool that's both powerful and a joy to
use give clubhouse a try designed for
software teams clubhouse is a fast
modern alternative to conventional
project management tools that are either
too complex or too simple start your
free trial and get 2 extra free months
at clubhouse io / se radio welcome to
software engineering radio
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Justin richer Justin richer is
a security architect software engineer
standards editor and systems designer
with nearly two decades of industry
experience he is the lead author of Roth
- in action and contributed to auth - an
open ID connect Justin was the editor of
the OAuth extensions RFC seven five nine
one seven five nine two seven six six
two and wrote vectors of trust
RFC eight four eight five justin is also
the co-author of the US federal digital
identity guidelines nist SP 800 - 6-3
he's also the editor of the heart
specifications as well as contributing
editor to you ma - quite impressive he
is also the founder maintainer of the
mitre ID connect
project and the who off X Y Zed a
security protocol project Justin welcome
to software engineering radio is there
anything I missed in your bio that you'd
like to add no thank you very much for
having me on yeah that it's it's
definitely a bit of an alphabet soup in
the bio there so I'm impressed that you
got through all of the RFC numbers and
everything good yeah first time they'll
be um tons of links on the show notes ER
we can all look up the RFC fantastic
okay so during the show we'll be talking
about OAuth 2 the industry standard
protocol for authorization I'd like to
start with an overview of what al off 2
is and move on to some key features and
then go through some specific examples
Justin can you explain briefly what the
earth is and the difference between
version 1 and 2 absolutely o auth a lot
of times gets spoken of as an
authorization protocol because it's all
about allowing a piece of software to do
something for you but if you get down
into the weeds of what the protocol is
actually doing what it's really about is
it's actually a delegation protocol o
auth allows you to have a user who's got
a certain set of rights to an API and
allow that user to say hey I want this
piece of software that I'm using to use
this API on my behalf so the users not
really setting authorization policies
and it's not something like you know as
a camel where you're you're setting up
things that you know when I see this
kind of request this is the kind of
result that I'm looking for instead is a
protocol that allows you to set you can
think of it as a service specific
password in an automated fashion so your
application instead of taking in your
username and password you can use OAuth
to get what's called an OAuth access
token that can access the API in your
stead so that the application never sees
your credentials never even needs to
necessarily know who you are it just has
to go through the OAuth process and get
this token and then that token sort of
allows the software to act on your
behalf
ok now you asked ooofff 1 & 2
the differences are conceptually they're
very similar they're both delegation
protocols so they both allow a piece of
software to act on a user's behalf but
the differences are largely around how
they do that and the assumptions that
were made in their design now back when
oh uh one was designed literally in a
backroom at OSCON back in 2006 think of
what the internet looked like in 2006
the biggest website was myspace like
iPhone and Android weren't a thing
that's only thirteen years ago you know
it's right it's it's an absolutely
different world it's it's mind-blowing
to to think of that so what ooofff one
was trying to do was connect two
websites to each other and it did a
pretty decent job at that and it
actually did so well that big companies
like Google and Yahoo and a bunch of
others dropped support of their
proprietary versions of delegation
protocols authsub and bebe auth and a
bunch of others that sort of influenced
oo auth they drop support for their
proprietary versions and instead used
this new open standard that kind of came
out of the community now o auth one kind
of suffered from its success because
people started using it and it came
about right around when the Internet as
we know it was changing people were
starting to build API driven websites
mobile applications we're starting to
become a more important thing and the
way that people are interacting with
things on the web or even what we know
of as you know interacting on the web
and on the Internet at all and so a lot
of the assumptions that went into OAuth
1 really weren't fitting with all of the
different places that people were trying
to use it so a group of us got together
and tried to take the best parts of
OAuth 1 and sort of streamline it into a
sort of core protocol that people could
use in a variety of different ways so
while both one was a monolithic protocol
there was only one way to do everything
all the time both to
is more of a it's it's a bunch of
ingredients that's packed with some
common recipes that say like oh you've
got a web server based application oh
you've got a in browser application
you've got a server to server
application here's how you take these
parts and put them together to do that
but also with the flexibility to come up
with your own ways to make your own
recipes if you will excellent that
brings me on to the next section where I
want to break those scenarios down into
a couple of examples so you mentioned in
the intro there that the fundamental
uses so a user or something that's
trying to access a protected resource
doesn't get your private credentials ie
in and there's a first example username
and password right because if you change
that password like you're supposed to do
you'll then have to change it everywhere
all the time so I think most of us are
used to seeing this type of interaction
when we allow another application to
access our details for example say
Dropbox or logging in with a Google
account or basically just approving
access for something which I would put
into the traditional web based client
server type model mhm yeah that's that's
really the world that OAuth came from
and it really was a reaction to you know
web api's were being built and deployed
with this pattern of just protecting
whim protect them with HTTP basic auth
and just ask for the users username some
of the biggest problems with that are
not just the fact that you're exposing
the user's password but also once you
have the user's username and password
there's no differentiating between the
user doing something interactively
themselves and something acting on that
user's behalf yeah so when you come to
like audit logs and figured out what
went wrong exactly it's just this user
logged in and we only know it's that
user because we saw their password but
it might not have been them because it
might have been a piece of software that
they had typed their password into
twelve months ago we we really have no
way to tell the difference and the OAuth
token base
model allows you to basically create a
new credential that represents just that
piece of delegated software working for
that user instead of that user and all
of the rights that they may have to
whatever API it is that you're
protecting okay and I also just wanted
to to touch on something you mentioned
real quick if I may take a quick aside
yes and you mentioned changing passwords
like we were supposed to so a lot of the
conventional wisdom that people have
today is that you're supposed to change
your passwords regularly you know every
six months every year or something like
that
and as one of the major revisions in the
NIST digital identity guidelines one of
the things that we did was we actually
rescinded that advice okay because
research has shown that that actually
causes users to create weak passwords
people at the end of the day are going
to need to type these things in they're
going to need to remember them so
they're gonna come up with an easily
guessable and easily exploitable pattern
so the advice is now to change your
password only if there's been a
suspected breach or in terms of like you
know you are revalidating the account
and you know Reap roofing somebody after
an absence or something like that then
yes definitely change your credentials
then but if you don't suspect a breach
you should not be changing your
passwords regularly and certainly don't
make your users do it and this goes back
to what was mentioned your bio at the
nist SP 800 yeah yep SB 863 version 3
okay thanks but obviously their voice
still stands off don't use the same
password for all your services oh yeah
absolutely
and that's one of the key strengths that
the OAuth token based model gives you is
that just as nearly a side effect of
this protocol you get a new password if
you will a new token for every single
service and for every single client
application so if you have five
different client applications all using
the same API so say you've got Twitter
on your phone you've got tweet deck in
your browser you've got you know a
Twitter on your tablet all of those are
going to be using different tokens when
they go talk to the
API because they are computer-generated
and the user never even has to see them
so they don't have to be memorized they
don't have to be memorable and the user
doesn't have to manage them at all it
all happens automatically within the
software and that automatically allows
both sides of the table as it were
tomorrow to who's doing walk because
everyone has a different identifiable
access token right exactly that's where
you can and a lot of large providers
have started doing heuristic based
monitoring of API access so it's not
just oh we saw your credential and we're
gonna let you in it's like we saw your
credential the timing makes sense you're
it doesn't look like you're in a weird
time zone it doesn't look like you're
coming from a weird Network you know
we've maybe got some device
fingerprinting that our installed mobile
app can do that we can check against
what you've done before and all of that
can be tied to this access token over
time yeah and that's similar to what
your banks do at the moment isn't it if
you're pretty much based in the UK or
the US and then all of a sudden a
transaction pops up in Italy mm-hmm then
they know something's wrong and you'll
get an email or a call yeah and the
financial industry has had a lot of
practice in in detecting anomalies like
this one of the interesting things that
we're seeing though is that in the
financial industry if something goes
wrong the bank can put your money back
like they they have funds that like if
somebody steals money and okay we can we
have insurance and we can put this back
but you can't give somebody back privacy
you can't give somebody back data that's
been stolen and copied wants to sleek to
sleep exactly and so we're seeing a lot
of these technologies that have been
pioneered in other in other realms
being applied in ways where the actions
that you have to do once you figure out
something is amiss are are really
different in a lot of cases they're
they're not necessarily well known ahead
of time like people haven't fully
figured out how you give somebody back
privacy like you know when their medical
record leaks like we don't even
necessary
we know what to do with that yet we're
figuring that out pretty much now yeah
cuz the traceability you know it's like
for example when someone famous a video
of them gets posted on Twitter or
something or shared you can trace the
original share but you don't know if
it's pictures being taken or you know
once it's out there it's out there
yeah and that gets into the nature of
digital media to view something you have
to copy it first
that's just how networks work yeah the
nature of digital media is that you have
to copy it before you can view it so
when something goes across the network
it of necessity exists in both places
both the sender and the receiver and as
soon as I have viewed it I have a copy
of it and I quite frankly can remix that
and do whatever I like on my end with my
software and then republish that in a
format that's maybe got a caption on it
maybe got a border on it maybe it's part
of some larger piece maybe it's clipped
down you know there's there's a lot of
things that that can be done and so yeah
you're absolutely right that it's it's
not as simple as just tracing oh this is
where the leak first happened because
you know as as a lot of breaches of data
have shown us it's the it's kind of that
long tail of after-effects where the the
really interesting and strange things
start to happen yeah because if you have
us fine-grained control as we'll touch
upon shortly once it's being leaked or
out there it's like not having any
protection at all yep
given that example and of course always
fighting against this is the notion that
you know it's easy to just keep
everything locked up and never share it
but people want to share things but only
on their own terms you know so a system
that just doesn't allow data go out ever
nobody's gonna use it nobody's gonna
care and so it's it's a constant balance
so where does the nature of
come in so if we take the example I want
to start off with which is the
traditional web based client server so
I'll go on to a website I can't be
bothered to sign up for it so I'll use
the sign up a Facebook or sign up with
Google which I know behind the scenes is
the oauth2 type interaction the pop-up
or the redirection will happen and I'll
say the app I'm logging in to you once
access to your Facebook email other
things because I'm a technically savvy
user if the applications asking for my
dear birth or my friends list I'm
immediately concerned about that but if
it's just saying I just want to share my
email so I don't have to type in my
password how can I trust it this is an
ongoing area of research of how to
manage these consent and authorization
ceremonies with users in ways that both
inform them and also don't necessarily
just scare people off unnecessarily
would you like to take us through the
sort of traditional web based client
server Oh off to dance
so you're the user logging on to a
website all right so I'm actually gonna
use an example of not logging on to a
website because as you know and as many
of your listeners know that would be an
authentication transaction that's that's
identity that's figuring out who's there
Oh auth fundamentally is delegating
authorization so let's say that instead
of logging on to a website what I'm
trying to do is you know the canonical
example from the OAuth world is say I've
got a bunch of photos and I want to send
them to a photo printing service all
right somebody who's gonna make you know
nice little bounded book and mugs and
things like that I need to get my photos
there traditionally sure I could have
like downloaded them and then re
uploaded them to the website but it's a
lot easier if I can go to the photo
printing service and say hey my photos
are hosted over here you know you speak
this API I just allow you to go get my
photos from over there okay so what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna show up at the
photo printer the photo printer at this
point has no idea who I am
maybe I create an account or whatever
but that's all just local to the photo
printer
and it's gonna say oh I know how to
speak photo storage site right
maybe it's Dropbox maybe it's onedrive
maybe it's Flickr maybe it's Facebook
you know whatever I know how to speak
this API so if you allow me access to
this I'll go get your photos so that we
can print them and you know you can make
your family calendar or whatever so what
the user is going to see is they are
going to end up being redirected over to
their photo storage site and again this
is all web-based applications so I'm
going to be sitting on my browser at the
photo printer and it's gonna say you
know click here to go get your photos
from over there so I'm gonna like okay
I'm gonna click here and we'll just
we'll use Dropbox as an example so I'm
gonna click here and I'm gonna be sent
to Dropbox and then while I am at
Dropbox
there are things within that redirect
that Dropbox will be able to recognize
that this is an OAuth transaction so the
Dropbox server is able to say oh this is
a request for photos connecting to into
the API drop map Dropbox
now needs to know who I am so I can
authenticate their Dropbox can maybe
give me multi-factor challenges maybe a
you know ping me on a device that it
already knows is pre-registered Dropbox
can do whatever it wants here the
underlying OAuth protocol absolutely
doesn't care all Dropbox cares about is
that it knows who I am and it's sure
that it knows who I am
that way it knows whose photos are gonna
be passed along Dropbox can then prompt
me and say oh hey you know photo
printing site you know Snapfish or
whatever wants to be able to print
photos that are stored here and so I can
say well yeah I was just there wanting
to get my photos printed and they want
access to my photos this all makes sense
so I'm going to hit this I'm going to go
back there I can tell as a user I can
very easily knit together a story and to
tell myself as to what's going on
between these two systems so then I get
sent back
to the photo printer site at that point
the photo printer site has a little
piece of information called an
authorization code which it can then go
talk directly to the photo sharing site
and say oh hey somebody I don't know who
it is I don't know their user name I
don't know who you know them as I don't
even know what this is necessarily good
for because nobody told me just somebody
gave me this code you know I want you to
validate this and I'm also going to you
know the photo printing site is going to
authenticate itself so that the photo
sharing site knows that it's them that's
asking and it's going to hand that code
over and say all right if this is good
then give me something that I can use to
actually access your API so at that
point I've walked up to the print
service I've looked to see what storage
services and supports I've done my
Dropbox click Dropbox the print service
knows that I worked at Dropbox so it's
redirected me to the standard Dropbox
prompt to say Snapfish or whoever wants
to access your account at that point in
the full service doesn't know who I am
and doesn't care about anything to do
with me it just knows that it's off to
go and speak to Dropbox I'll then do SMS
verification one-time password or
whatever I've set up on my Dropbox
account yep and then the application or
the service requesting access to my
storage has got the first step of the
process which is the user's authorize me
to access and I've got this
authorization token but I still can't do
anything with it yeah at this point
exactly that authorization code isn't
enough on its own to access the API that
needs to be presented back to Dropbox to
our photo storage site in concert with
authentication of the printing site
because when the user authorized this
they did it in the context of presumably
coming from a specific photo printing
site and so that context needs to come
back and be applied to alongside this
authorization code
so when that shows up the photo storage
site can now say like oh yeah I
recognize this authorization code is it
and I issued it fairly recently because
you know this transaction is gonna take
a matter of seconds at most so these
things are not long-lived and in fact I
issued it to this specific photo
printing site and so what I want to be
able to do is give this photo printing
site something that will allow it to
access the photo storage API s but only
for the user that authorized and only
for whatever parts of the API that the
user authorized it for on that second
bit of requirement is what the serviced
asked Dropbox to be able to do so on the
thing that presents the user it says
this service wants to access your files
yeah exactly although the what I've
painted is a highly idealized version of
it reality gets really squirrely really
fast okay because you've got the
convolution of what the printing site
which would be the client in OAuth
parlance okay what the client has
requested what the user has authorized
what's even available at the API because
not all a the is aim you know maybe I
get only read access maybe I get only
image data and not metadata you know
because what does a printer need to know
the lat/longs that are associated with
my photos all right excited they
shouldn't they shouldn't be given that
information unless I have it unless they
have a need for it but the API needs to
be able to support that level of
granularity and the user needs to be
able to have approved that all of that
gets sort of bundled up the result of
all of that rather gets bundled up into
this access token which is what then
gets handed back to the client okay but
the access token is the next step after
they've got the authorization token
mm-hmm authorization code code yeah yes
to be pedantic okay that's good so the
for services got
authorization code how does Dropbox or
the storage system prove or challenge
that the printer service is legitimate
and it's who it thinks it is that's a
great question
and it's it's germane to sort of where
oh oh finds itself today as opposed to
when I ought to was ratified which was
between 2010 and 2012
not quite then entire internet age away
but getting close to it so when of' one
was written it was assumed that it was
always websites talking to what other
websites and so that all client
applications in all authorization
servers would have access to effectively
shared secrets that they could prove
possession of at all times
Oh auth to atleast admitted that not all
client applications are able to do that
if you have for example an instance of a
mobile application on one phone and then
you have the same instance of that
mobile application on a thousand other
phones if you're pre-packing a secret
into all of those mobile applications
it's not very secret anymore
and it's not particularly great at truly
confirming and identifying it but at the
time the most common and most canonical
use case was still two web servers
talking to each other and in those cases
the client application in this case the
photo printer goes and tells the
authorization server hey I got this
authorization code and here's this
secret that I have that proves that I am
this specific application and this is
what I am going to use to identify my
application that is asking on behalf of
this specific user because the client
secret is probably something Dropbox has
given it when it did its integration to
get access to Dropbox and get listed on
the approved apps or you know
integration yes exactly
yeah the the assumption and honestly the
practice is in a lot of cases you have
what's called a static registration so a
developer or assisted
for the client application pulls up a
console or sends in an application so a
developer or a company would go to their
developer console or their develop a
program sign hola contra exactly and so
that you know you know who to sue when
something goes wrong this is this is a
static registration and so they fill out
all of the contact information fill out
all of the information about the
application and things like that and
then at the end of that they get issued
an identifier and a secret that
identifier is what gets sent through the
browser when the user gets redirected
that's how we know that it's at least
probably going to be this application
that's asking for it though it is a
public piece of information anybody can
see it anybody could pretend at that
stage but it's when it comes back with
the authorization code that you actually
see the secret which nobody else should
have access to you yeah so that initial
token could be stolen or fished or
whatever but it's not until it's
challenged when it sends it back to get
the actual access right exactly and with
web servers and sort of all other
variables being relatively equal that's
a pretty decent way to protect access to
these tokens to keep them from being
issued to malevolent parties mm-hmm
since you mentioned mobile ops I think
we could move onto that and come back to
you a bit more detail on them yeah of
course additional client server you
obviously can't have a client secret
saved on a device because normally that
would be the photo services back-end
systems are protected mm-hm
and it's only known to that company what
options are open to mobile app
developers to use a standard based
protocol I go auth too so that's a great
question and that's again one of the key
differences in Roth 2 was admitting that
mobile apps existed okay because well
when a while one was was brought
together they kind of didn't they I mean
there were heavyweight desktop
applications of course but
not the type of Anthony P I economies
that we have today that we should
probably define a mobile apps ah yeah
great point we're not talking like
Safari or Firefox browsers are on a
device we're talking about either a
native app that's written and Swift or
Java Android or iOS or some type of
wrapper around that but it lives on the
device it has access to the storage it
might be through the same API so the
browser can say things but fundamentally
it's saving a token or some type of data
on that device right exactly it's
something that runs and lives and
executes on the device itself and
outside of the context of the system
browser so it may have it may make use
of web and browser based technologies
but it's not necessarily a browser-based
application because it's not something
that you're fetching from a remote
server and running inside your system
browser with all of your cookies and
sessions and tabs and everything else it
really is running in its own own little
world own little space it's interesting
to make that point today because again
that was something that that wasn't
really a thing that people were doing
when we were writing OAuth 2 there was a
much brighter line between web-based
applications
browser-based applications and native
applications so stuff that was running
on a desktop or on a mobile platform
these days the technologies you've you
know JavaScript runs absolutely
everywhere and there's all sorts of
wrappers and repackage errs and cross
compilers and and things like that for
lots of different languages and
platforms such that you don't really you
can't predict how an application is
going to function based on just the
language that it's written in anymore
ok so the main difference though is sort
of the assumptions of the execution
environment and the interaction methods
that are available to that application
yeah so you could treat the won't call
it a native app that's the back
system of the service mm-hmm so your
options might be to present the user
with a login so you put in your username
and password or there's some type of
automatic registration of that
application right so the options for
dealing with these mobile apps are or
native apps in general as you mentioned
you could take instead of doing a static
registration you could do what's called
a dynamic registration okay and this is
where the instance of the client
application software it wakes up it
knows that it's in order to talk to this
API it needs to go talk to a specific
authorization server but it's gonna wake
up and realize it doesn't have a client
identifier it doesn't have any client
secrets or keys or anything like that
associated with it it needs to go get
something but it would know it would
know the end point now it's probably the
bare minimum it would need exactly and
even then there are extensions to OAuth
that allow for resource based discovery
for for common api's such as overnight
econnect that you can discover all of
that from a single piece of user input
but once you know which authorization
server you need to talk to the client
software basically shows up it makes a
call directly to the server and says hi
I'm a piece of software this is what I'm
called here's where my home page is
here's the contact email of my developer
here's my redirect URI uses the kinds of
keys that I can manage let's go and the
server then can make sense of that
request and come back to the client with
a client identifier most importantly and
in a lot of cases a client secret now we
had just said before that if you have a
mobile application and it's installed on
a million different devices you know a
client secrets not secret anymore
okay but that's only if you put the
secret into the software before it goes
out that's what I would call a
configuration time secret all right
something that happens in the developers
hands part of the build process or
deployment process like that's not going
to stay secret but if we can turn that
into a runtime secret then mobile apps
do just fine
with that yeah you know if you're using
best practices for system storage
there's even security enclaves where you
can store things on today's platforms
that are covered by localized biometrics
there's a lot of things that you can do
to store and manage runtime secrets yeah
you could install it on os's keychains
or iCloud or whatever operating system
it is you could store it for the
lifetime of the apps on and then it does
the dance again but how when it comes
alive and says I'm here I need to do
something what what do you use in that
process to prove that that client is
something you know about or you allow
access so it turns out that's a really
really difficult thing to do in the real
world and there are a handful of
approaches to that chicken-and-egg is
not it really is because there's really
no difference between interoperability
and unknown request from an unknown
third party like if you're being truly
end to end like open and interoperable
people can just show up and start
picking your proto speaking your
protocol that's that's kind of the point
but that's also kind of the problem and
so we've got some things built into the
dynamic client registration protocol you
know auth and I should probably here
point out that I served as the editor in
the ITF for that specification
yeah that's RFC seven five nine one and
we'll have a link there right yeah I've
got that already tonight all right
fantastic is this a new extension - off
- no no that's that is now several years
old I would honestly it's in your book
so it's not yeah it's it's it's it's
quite a few years old at this point it's
it's pretty well-established
it's just not something exhausting above
and beyond a normal interaction not
really exotic and it's certainly it's
not a it's not a very complicated
protocol that's for sure but what it is
though is it's something that lets you
set up the environment for especially
for native apps but web server based
apps can use this too and browser base
apps can use this too it sets off the
environment so that all of those
assumptions about which secrets are in
place which I did
fires are in place before the OAuth
protocol even starts those can all
actually be put there beyond just
developer and okay if you couldn't or if
you didn't want to use the dynamic
registration type model for a browser or
a mobile app what options would you have
to not do well in our - you need to have
a client identifier nope no matter what
no matter what I mean that's that's
absolutely core to the protocol and so
you need to get it in there whether it
gets configured whether it gets built in
as part of the deployment because you
could have for example sort of a device
and platform management system that when
it issues an instance of an application
it can do the registration and pack that
stuff into the that instance for you so
it can you could have a back-end system
do the dynamic registration at install
time you know that's that's an option at
which point you can start using some of
the additional protections that we have
built into the dynamic client
registration protocol in ways that make
sense so when you do that initial
registration you're allowed to pass on
to things that could help identify you
the first of those is what's called a
software statement this is a signed
assertion it's actually a JSON web token
format that basically just says these
are the attributes that this client
should be asking for you know whoever
shows up with this this is sort of the
the fingerprint of this application if
you will and it's been signed by a third
parties trusted key so that doesn't
necessarily mean that whatever piece of
software is presenting it is supposed to
be presenting it because we've never
seen the software before if they had
signed it with their own key we have no
way of knowing it's their own key
because we've never talked to them
before but what it does at least allow
us to do is look at a piece of software
and say that oh it's at least going to
behave in a certain way so if somebody
is going to be impersonating an
application to the point of
impersonating their redirect URIs and
their home pages and everything like
we're going to see more anomalous
behavior on that specific application
that's something we can at least try to
look out for and that's an attack we
have to look out for anyway because of
you know locally modified applications
and you know captured systems and
whatnot then we can use that software
statement to kind of lock down the
behavior during the registration process
so that if one of those software
statements starts getting abused we can
effectively put a lasso around everybody
that use that software statement and go
okay you know what we're gonna yank that
back and we're gonna issue a new
software statement through some trusted
out-of-band channel however we got it to
you guys in the first place maybe that
you have to use from now on and anytime
we see this old one or any registrations
based on this old one we're not gonna
honor them anymore yeah because you've
got quite a lot of options in the what
you call the dance to detect anomalies
there's lots of requests for grants and
codes you know something's up or as if
it's just someone log in and click and
send you block them but at that time
they've got you know more information
than they should write so say you have
an application that is that you know is
a mobile application and so they've
signed up to use the authorization code
grant type and somebody tries to do a
dynamic registration of that that signs
up to use the implicit grant type okay
well you've immediately know something's
up because you're that that piece of
software is not supposed to have that
piece of functionality somebody's trying
to do something weird and so that's
something that you can kind of
immediately start to lock down and
detect and that's just a very simple
superficial example summers longer days
and slower pace invite us to pick up a
book follow our questions and try our
hand at something new the work of modern
software developers is evolving in ways
that are both challenging and rewarding
as a developer it's essential that you
cultivate a security mindset to help we
put together a collection of information
security books podcasts blogs and
hands-on exercises recommended by very
coders across our development security
and product teams from a just published
page-turner to classic frack articles
there's something here for everyone
who's interested in becoming more
security minded
so dip your toes in or take a deep dive
visit www.opm.gov/life and eyes on for
the token park because in this packets
it wasn't clear but it is now that the
JSON web tokens is sort of the preferred
manner and then we can dig into the
different grant types which will help us
pick which one to use for which specific
use case in the examples so it makes
sense yeah absolutely and no that's
that's a great set of topics especially
because the JSON web token is not
necessarily the preferred type but we'll
get back to that in just a sec I look
forward to it so open ID and
specifically open ID connect was built
as an identity layer on top of OAuth 2
okay when open ID Connect was being
ratified we looked at sort of the
classic open ID systems which were a you
know a redirect based very very website
focused identity protocol and a woth one
which was a very website focused
authorization protocol and it was really
really really difficult to cram the two
together even though people wanted to
because as it turns out in the real
world
nobody wants pure authentication nobody
wants to just know oh you have logged in
the end and I don't care anything else
about you I don't want to access
anything I just want to know somebody
logged in nobody ever does that
similarly nobody ever does pure
authorization they almost always want to
know something about the user even if
it's just a display name or an email
address so that they can contact the
user if something goes wrong with their
printing order for example okay so
people were very very interested in
using these two technologies together
but when we were developing oh oh off
too you know so I helped work on both
auth to and open ID Connect neither I
will be very clear that neither was my
idea I'm not taking that much credit for
it I was just
fortunate enough to be part of those
conversations but the idea with open ID
Connect is that you start with this
authorization protocol of oauth2 right
you have the user show up and you are in
their authorizing access to something
and that's the key pet is that it's an
authorization protocol exactly but the
question is what are they authorizing
access to okay with open ID connect what
you are authorizing access to is your
identity information so you treat your
identity instead of your treating the
authentication as the primary thing I
have to know who you are and then I'll
figure out you know what I'm gonna let
you do first
like whoever you are authorize me to do
things and one of the things I want you
to authorize is for me to know who you
are
so it kind of flips things on their head
but in a way that actually makes a lot
of sense because alongside of who you
are I also want to know all right so now
let me download your pictures so that I
can print them right now let me post to
your newsfeed now let me send messages
to your friends you know whatever else
that I wanted to do with it that API is
in addition to knowing who you are and
as a consequence open ID Connect and
similar identity protocols that are out
there are really I would say far and
away the most common uses of oauth2 that
we've got and unfortunately that means
that many many many people think of
OAuth 2 as an authentication protocol or
as well as a login system yeah because
there are so many login systems that are
based on that and to to clear this up
you know my favorite metaphor from this
I stole this from a fantastic engineer
named Vittorio if you treat Oh auth
think of it like chocolate all right it
is a fantastic ingredient you can have
it on its own but you can also make a
lot of different recipes with it
authentication an open ID Connect that's
more like a chocolate cake you know it
takes a few different ingredients put
together in the right way to come up
with this specific thing
and can you make a cake without
chocolate absolutely there's a lot of
different ways that you can throw a few
common things together but when you're
having chocolate cake you're you're
noticing the chocolate you're noticing
that that you know that's kind of the
key thing that's standing out even
though it's coming to you in the form of
this cake although there are a lot of
other ingredients that have to go in
there like the other thing is that you
can make a lot of different things with
chocolate you can make chocolate fudge
you can make you know chocolate cream
pies you can you can make you know hot
coco lots of different things with it
that have nothing to do with chocolate
cake
I often open idea are really the same
way an open-eyed eConnect was an attempt
to you know to overstretch the metaphor
here come up with a an international
standard for chocolate cake recipes so
that when people are building an
identity protocol like here's something
that tells you exactly what to do that
can build you this using OAuth 2 as the
primary sort of cornerstone ingredient
and does so in a way that is secure and
repeatable and interoperable and
functional yeah and you don't want to
have to reinvent things if there's
something out there everyone's using
then you're gonna reach for it
absolutely absolutely although
unfortunately the last number of years
have shown us that a lot of developers
fall into the trap of thinking that it
would be easier for them to reinvent
things don't just try to think some of
my use cases to see if I'm one of it
it's extraordinarily common and so I
work as a consultant now and there have
been a lot of times where I have walked
into a group and like very very smart
and enthusiastic engineers who said hey
look we built this thing and I'd looked
like do you know that there's you know
this RFC that says how to do like ninety
percent of what you're doing and also
doesn't have this fixation vulnerability
that you guys didn't see so I would love
to say that yes engineers don't want to
reinvent wheels but let's face it we do
but when doing that we should at least
you know I've done it too but we should
at least be aware
what wheels are out there so that
whatever we're building ends up round
you know yeah you know we we don't want
to repeat the mistakes that other people
have already figured out the answers to
I understand
cool so I think we spoke about tokens a
lot so yeah those that haven't heard of
but I'm pretty sure most people will JWT
so JSON web tokens I seem to think
they're the standard way to do things
but you've rightly corrected me yeah
they are a standard way and they're
probably far and away the most common
structured self-contained token format
in the OAuth world question about that
but there are a lot of spaces still that
use unstructured Roth tokens so the
thing about OAuth is that in both a auth
one and OAuth 2 it doesn't care what
this token is that you get out the far
end it doesn't care what its format is
doesn't care what it's made of it's just
it's got to be you got to be able to put
it into an HTTP header and other than
that you know all bets are off is it
something the client needs to know
horrors are just gonna pass it back and
forth the client is just a dumb carrier
of it especially in - going back to the
differences in version 2 of the protocol
one of the things that we wanted to do
was allow client applications to be as
dumb as possible because you got to
think about when you're designing
security for a system like this you got
to think about what motivations a client
developer has or the developers of the
different aspects of the system so the
authorization server its job is to be a
security component right you want your
best security engineers to be working on
that to make sure like all of the
different error branches are doing the
right thing that trace backs aren't
sending bad things and into weird places
stuff like that think about a client
developer though they have something
that they're trying to use an API like
that's what they're trying to get done
at the end of the day they security is
something that gets in the way of
somebody doing something awesome yeah
right and so security systems I
fundamentally and deeply believe need to
be able to
live in the real world where they
function when people don't actually care
about them like if you can give somebody
a very simple recipe to follow say like
do this do this do this and it works out
pretty well then I think that you're
doing a pretty good job
and so with OAuth tokens the client has
no idea what the format of the token is
so that left space in the OAuth 2 world
for innovation as to what to put into
these tokens and and for some
standardization and as as you rightly
pointed out the leading structure for
token information is a jot JWT JSON web
token and that is RFC 75 1/9 not to be
confused with RFC 75 9 one that we've
talked about in order to be confused
with RFC seven one five minute JSON
which I swear that the RFC editor was
trolling me when she assigned RFC seven
five nine one which had dependencies on
seven five one nine and seven one five
nine for the list there's just look at
the links at the end yeah there's it's
it's a soup of numbers and if you've
although I will say encourage any of
your listeners you know if you come hang
out with us in the IETF the internet
Engineering Task Force the standards
body where these get defined you'll be
speaking in four-digit numbers before
you know it and the weird thing is the
people around you will understand what
you mean it's very it's a stranger yeah
I've actually joined the working group
and see some of your comments on the
OAuth stuff we're yeah we're we're happy
to have you there it is open membership
you don't have to pay anything you don't
even have to get lawyers to sign off on
anything just know that anything that
you contribute is considered to
contribution unless if standard base
work and RFC's you know it's all the
product of collaboration it really is
and the job specification
[Music]
let's go back let's go back right the
job specification was designed as a way
to communicate information about what's
been delegated from the authorization
server to the resource server okay now
back in sort of traditional oo auth
world yeah and if you even look at the
spec for OAuth 1 there was no
differentiation between authorization
server and resource server it was just
server because the assumption was that
you had one machine that was running
your API and you're gonna have a
function on that machine that generates
and manages these tokens so how do I
know what a token is you know when a
client makes a call to an API how does
that resource know what that token is
well it's just gonna go look it up in
the same database that it keeps
everything else in mm-hmm as the world
started to get more distributed and to
their credit Google really pushed a lot
of the standards community in this
direction thinking about more widely
distributed systems from early days the
resource server needs to have other
methods to figure out what this token is
good for and one of those methods is to
just put information into the token
itself so when the token shows up it's
can carry a signature so I can make sure
that it was issued and signed by
somebody whose key that I've trusted and
the token itself can tell me like yeah
this is for this set of API s and this
set of actions at these api's within
this time window for this specific user
you can carry all of that information
inside of the JSON web token the
downside of this is you're carrying all
of that information inside the JSON web
token mm-hm and if you're back to the
same problem of the client signature
secret exactly saying that oh well
because because the well the client is
not signing this at all this is signed
by the authorization server and the
client just carries just valid a and I
it issued the token itself exactly
exactly so it doesn't doesn't give you
any protection about who's presenting
the token it only gives you information
about who issued the token so that's
that's another downside with jots is
that people sometimes mistakenly think
it's giving you more
than it then it actually is in terms of
protection and sort of locking down the
system there are two other big drawbacks
to JA and you know as with any system
there are benefits and drawbacks one of
the drawbacks is with all of this
information packed into the token it not
only gets potentially large but it also
could be bad for privacy
okay so what's in a token it's JSON yep
it's it's JSON that's been wrapped up in
its own special format so if you look at
it it'll look like gibberish to a human
but it is actually base64 URL encoded
JSON okay which is why most jots start
with the characters
ey capital J zero yeah because that's
the base64 encoding of an open curly
braket oh that makes sense
but it just it's three parts isn't it
yep so you've got the first signed jots
you have a header which is basically
your cryptographic envelope information
you've got your payload which says who
issued the token it's sort of time
constraints x brie and whatnot its
audience constraints who the token was
issued to who it was authorized by so
you know potential user names and things
like that and then you've got the
signature that is over that whole system
one of the key innovations of the jaw
specification is that the signature is
calculated over that base64 URL encoded
JSON as it's presented to you over the
wire previous versions of signature
based document systems like XML D cig
and even some modern systems like
json-ld signatures require you to
transform and normalize the document
before you process or check the
signature with a JSON web token you take
it literally as is which means it's very
easy to get right and with a
cryptographic system that is absolutely
a feature that you want to have you know
you want people to be able to get good
signatures and validate good signatures
very very easily because otherwise what
people do is they'll just they'll turn
off signature validation if the
normalization is screwing up one day
like okay well we'll turn this off and
we'll turn it on later it'll be fine
yeah and of course we all know that
doesn't happen so your your jaw is three
lots of base64 you can if you if you saw
on your screen you'd see the three full
stops we knew that separate that's true
exactly there yeah there for a sign jot
it's a base64 URL encoded JSON than a
period a full stop then another one of
those and then a period and then a
base64 URL encoded binary blob which is
the signature okay and you could paste
that into a service to decode that can
yeah yep exactly and even without you
know there are lots of libraries to do
that today but even without access to
libraries you really only need string
split so split it on the period
character base64 URL decode to get your
three sections and then json.parse the
first two okay that doesn't give you
signature validation but it'll at least
let you parse the payloads and headers
and and let you kind of run that through
your system without even a jot library
and that's why you have to be really
careful about what you put in the token
because it's very easy to to see it
exactly it even though the client
doesn't care what's in the token that's
a large that's a far cry from the client
not being able to see what's in the
token and so which is one of the reasons
why there are also encrypted jots which
are instead of three sections there are
five sections because you've got the
encryption key and the encrypt payload
and the integrity vector and all these
other bits and pieces and those when you
base64 URL decode the payload you're
gonna get encrypted gibberish because it
has to be further decrypted based on
okay some key that the resource server
would have to know but the trade-off
here of course is that now the resource
server needs to have access to the
private decryption key for that job
whereas before it just needed to know
the the public signing key of the
issuing server which is really easy to
distribute and make available because
it's public and what would you recommend
if someone's thinking of not only user
know
- were using GWT charts for anything
well I would actually recommend that you
first consider a second major drawback
here and that's that jots are themselves
they contain their own state which means
that a jot is going to tell you if that
jot is still valid which is a really
great thing if you've got disadvantaged
networks and you know and you want
things to be highly performant
everything can be processed locally but
the downside there there's no way to
revoke a jot once it's in flight if
nobody's going to be doing any checks on
that like because the jot itself is
going to say that it's valid and if
you're only checking the draw itself
you'll never know that somebody went and
revoked it yeah there's a lot of talk
around using those tokens for session
cookie replacements you know and in your
browser and which brings me on to the
other example of single page JavaScript
type apps
well they'll go and request and save a
token in the browser but then you have
that exact problem you just explain
where you can't expire it you kind of
date it because you've messed with a
signature right
you can't revoke it so once it's been
saved on that user's browser it's
vulnerable to all the different types of
attacks out there it is the attacks and
the information leakage like we were
talking about before so one of the
things that we did with the Hart profile
that you mentioned in the intro there
that's right I'll put a big circle
around that to make sure it's in the
show notes absolutely so one of the
things that we did with the Hart
profiles is that that's a set of
profiles for OAuth to open ID connect
and user manage access or uma that are
specific to the healthcare world and on
your accessing health records the you
know that's the clever name for the for
the working group heart but when you're
working in the healthcare world there
are a lot of times where the the number
of checks that security checks that you
want to make are going to be kind of
dependent on what is being asked for
like if somebody is getting just like
really broad
a graphic research information and stuff
like that it's like okay and I've seen
this token again from the same place
within a couple of seconds then yeah you
know I really don't need to check this
again but if somebody is getting say you
know HIV status information for a
specific patient and I've never seen
this token before and the token looks
like it was actually issued a while ago
but I'm only just now seeing it because
all of that information can be encoded
in the jaw well I might want to be able
to go look that up you know or go to the
financial world if somebody is just
checking their basic account balances
you want that to be nice and fast nice
and performant you can just check the
information in the jaw itself but then
when you get to that next step of yeah
and now I want you to send money or I
want you to send a lot of money you
really really want to make sure that
token is still good right so at that
point you can go and use a protocol
called OAuth token introspection and
that's a really simple web protocol
where the resource server can go talk
back to the authorization server and say
hey one it can authenticate itself so I
am this resource server you've seen me
before and somebody just gave me this
token what is it good for you know is it
still active who was it issued to all of
that stuff you can then put all of that
information in the response of that
introspection call instead of having to
bake it into the token plus it allows
you to go in and validate at runtime
that the token is still there you know
it's still good it's a double layer of
politician exactly both jaw and
introspection were defined separately
but they can be used together and that's
one of the things that we did with the
heart specifications and token
introspection incidentally that is
what's behind RFC you know that is RFC
766 to and again I helped serve it as
the editor for that one okay so uh you
know I've had a lot of people ask ask me
kind of what you know what would I
recommend what I recommend jots what I
recommend introspection and it largely
depends on like what is it that you're
actually trying to accomplish and we've
seen the same sort of
back and forth pull in the security
space for many many years
I mean look at what we do with web PKI
now right you get a certificate and the
certificate itself has signatures on it
from a CA that has probably been pre
placed and prepackaged and dropped into
your browser and that's all very fast
check you know highly performant highly
scalable but we realize that you know a
revoked certificate is something that
people want to know about yeah
so we started publishing certificate
revocation lists those starts get on
wieldy so we came up with OCSP which is
a protocol that allows you to say hi I
just got a certificate is it any good
which might just sound familiar from the
description from the conversation we
were just having about token
introspection like none of this is
really new and and this brings me to if
I may one of my favorite jokes in
computer science there are really only
two heart problems in computer science
naming things cache consistency and
off-by-one errors yeah we hear that a
lot
in this ship and although it's one of my
favorite - I love that one and this is
very squarely cache consistency like
yeah when you get something yeah you
revolve it yeah exactly so introspection
allows you to do that runtime validation
but there's a cost to that you got to go
out across the network and figure out
you know and you got to make the call
and you got it have the resource servers
have things associated with them so that
you can validate them and all of that
other stuff okay could we quickly go
through the grant type auctions I would
have as a developer if we take the web
example the single page app example it's
a client base client based on server
based so if I'm doing a mobile art
absolutely yeah so this used to be a
much more not difficult question but a
question with a much longer answer
because these days best practice is
honestly to use the authorization code
flow for all of these different things
okay so used to be the recommendation
was to use what's called the implicit
flow for browser-based applications and
the implicit flow does everything
through browser redirects instead of
having these direct HTTP calls a large
reason for that was that back in 2010
JavaScript was very very limited cores
did not exist yeah as a technology but
these days we can nor did postmessage
nor did a lot of other stuff that we
have today and we can do a much much
better job cross-origin resource sharing
yeah where the browser's making the
request yeah exactly when the browser's
making a direct request within
JavaScript as opposed to a what we would
call a back-channel call and so now
JavaScript applications in browser
applications SBA's and alike can
actually do that and so that it makes a
lot more sense to use the authorization
code flow even in those spaces okay then
then it may be used to with native
applications the auth code flow has
always been the recommended best
practice but we have an additional
technology today called pixie that's
proof key for code exchange pke
and that's because you know nerds will
never turn down a chance to have a cute
name for something and what's clever
about pixie is that it allows you to
protect that exchange of the
authorization code without using a
client secret okay effectively what
you're doing is when you start off the
process the client creates a secret and
sends a hash of that secret with its
request its initial request for the
token and then when the authorization
code comes back to the client it sends
the unhatched secret along with the
authorization code and the authorization
server can then knit those two together
and say like oh yeah I saw the hash of
this secret before so I know that you
are the piece of software that made that
initial request even though you haven't
necessarily been pre-registered you know
yeah I have not given you some compile
time secret you haven't done
dynamic registration and you know you
can prove to me that you were the one
that started this transaction and so
people are looking at how new is that
pixie is also a few years old okay so
yeah pixie is very well-established if
you're working on mobile applications
today honestly I would tell all of your
listeners to use Google's app off
libraries for both Android and iOS and
yeah if we could provide a link to that
yeah I'm seriously taking about that
yeah and because that includes pixie it
includes but it also includes all sorts
of other sort of mobile best practices
just you know ensconced in an open
source library that you can just use so
you don't have to reinvent this we've
kind of got a clear choice now between
the ground type that was one of my
points or what to go through which is
the original one it yeah it really is
everything else in os/2 was invented as
an optimization of the authorization
code flow so the there are others one
that still does make sense is the client
credentials grant type but that's the
one you use when there's not a user
involved at all okay so you've got two
back-end systems where we would
traditionally use an API key the client
credentials grant gives you the ability
to effectively still have an API key but
that API key is for getting oo auth
tokens as opposed to getting the actual
API data the key here is that the
resource servers downstream now only
have to care about access tokens so they
get in an access token and they can
validate that we've got as we've been
talking about we've got the tools to do
that with introspection and JA and you
know database and service lookup type
stuff we can already do all of that we
no longer have to manage and distribute
API keys to however many API servers
there might be floating out there
it lets us centralize our concerns into
dedicated security components because I
know I would rather have a very very
strong
some might say single point of
failure but I would rather have one
strong single point of failure than a
hundred equally weak single points of
failure yeah you know yeah and you
mentioned the framework that you
recommend there I would guess that you
don't want to be ruling any of this
yourself no um you can get away with it
on the client side and do a decent
decent enough job but there's a lot of
best practice documents that you would
probably want to read up on there is a
best practice document from the IETF on
mobile applications there is one that is
being written right now for in browser
applications and that's the BCP yes yes
best current practice BCP and those sort
of collect all of the best advice oh and
one note I want to make about single
page apps before we get off this
entirely is that it turns out that the
way people are building and deploying
single page apps a lot of them don't
actually need OAuth ok
because just about every single page app
is gonna be talking to a first-party API
back-end which itself might need to go
do and talk to a third party API but it
turns out to be very rare for a an
application to really need anything more
than a session cookie to talk to its
back-end systems as an aside that's how
I've done something that I was working
on yes yeah issues a session cookie so
if there's one lesson you could teach
every developer out there regarding
authorization what would it be oh that's
a great question so I would say that
authorization is one of those things
that looks like it's really really
simple it's just oh I'm trying to call
my API and I need to do this thing I'm
so how hard could it be but there are so
many places that it can go sideways that
absolutely read the best practices use
not just libraries but you know trusted
libraries ooofff has been around long
enough that there's a lot of really good
well-established community work that's
out there that's available on any
platform that you can think of and also
you know keep an eye out for the fact
like we were just talking about with
single page apps that
sort of Oh auth and this authorization
delegation might not actually be the
solution that your problem needs you
know Oh auth is a tool it's a very
powerful and very elegant tool for doing
a one specific thing but it's not a
panacea you can't just add it to a
system and then magically get security
and a lot of the limitations of oo auth
is where the XYZ project that I'm
working on now is that's really where
we're trying to pick up from that okay
where can people find out more you know
more about your XYZ project or get
involved yeah so that is available on
the website o auth dot X Y Z and it's
named X Y Z because at a conference
dinner I bought the domain o auth dot X
Y Z on a bit of a lark and then a couple
of months later this project started up
so that's that's its name I will be
presenting this at the XYZ work at the
identifier conference in DC which will
unfortunately by the time listeners hear
this that will have passed okay but the
good news is that if if they weren't
there in person then videos of that
presentation will be made available
within the coming months yep and the
slides will be available too and I will
link those off of the OAuth to XYZ
website when those are made available as
well plus if you are getting involved
with the IETF oo-aah working group I
will be presenting this at Montreal and
we'll see if there's appetite in the
community for for moving the OAuth
protocol forward in this direction or
not but I think there's some exciting
stuff because oo auth has been a really
fantastic tool and it's gonna be around
for a long time I mean it does what it
does really really well but what's
really getting me excited now is solving
the problems that of' doesn't do well
and I think we're we're in a good
position to start really doing that okay
I look forward to getting you on again
fantastic I would be happy to happy to
come back any time
excellent Justin thank you for coming on
the show it's been a real pleasure and
you've answered all the things I've had
buzzing around my head for the past
couple of months and hopefully the
listeners too this is Gavin Henry for
software engineering radio thank you
listening thank you thanks for listening
to Nessie radio an educational program
brought to you by Triple E software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio slack calm you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening